All right, greetings everyone. Welcome
slashback.
It's September 18th and we're in chapter
8.
So to begin, is there anything that
anyone wants to bring up? a question
from the KOD or a section from the
textbook
could be in chapter 8 or just anything
that's top of mind if you want to start
there.
Just go for it or I'll I'll look in the
chat.
Um could you
uh
some context to the sort of philosophy
of science uh perspective on uh
continuous versus discrete modeling and
how uh maybe other
uh fields before active in inference um
have tried to approach this question.
>> Nice. Yes. Well, obviously a huge
question. It's a lot like the
complimentarity
between analog and digital. Like if you
have a cassette tape or a vinyl record,
no matter how much you zoom in, there's
always going to be some continuous
value to the signal. So like a radio
signal through the air or a physical
media like tape or vinyl. Whereas
digital
records
they have a sampling rate. So they are
like very rapidly
spaced samples you know asterisk
asterisk pending zooming in to very high
levels. So just at a first pass. Um, so
when it comes to modeling time,
which as the quote that starts the
chapter hints at, time can be modeled as
change. And in chapter 7 and in chapter
8, we're introduced to the two big ways
that time is modeled, which is in
chapter 7, in the discrete time case,
you have discrete time steps could be
very high frequency or could be big gaps
between them relatively. And then you
define transition functions or
transition matrices
which are iteratively applied. And so
that's the B matrix or here number three
on the top of figure 4.3. But that's a
transition matrix that gets applied. So
time step one you multiply by matrix you
get to time step two. There's nothing in
between one and two. There's just a rule
that moves you forward one click at a
time. There's no time step 1.1.
In contrast, in the continuous time
setting, it's more like you have a
string
and that string is going to be this
continuous differentiable function
through time. So
that has different pros and cons which
definitely we should explore and discuss
more.
But the big difference is continuous
time models are like a path or a string
through time. So they're continuous and
unbroken and differentiable everywhere.
In contrast, discrete models only have
values at specific intervals.
And there are pros and cons to handling
each of those. Which is why chapter 8
where we get to by the end is
what about a hierarchical mixed
generative model where you have a
continuous time model on the lower level
and a discrete model on the higher
level. like we will we will get there
today and talk about why that
architecture gets converged upon.
But this is kind of like the the whether
it's about time being continuous or
discreet or whether it's about space
being continuous or discreet.
That's definitely the ongoing debate.
And then when it comes to our digital
computers,
even the continuous time models,
you're going to have some digitized
interval
that's going to be used.
And does this
depend on the the
perception
or the action steps being continuous or
discrete because you know they can be
mixed and matched but it seems like it
depends on the input
uh classification.
>> Yes. Um so seven and eight focus on
discrete and continuous time
settings. But then there's also
separately from how time is handled. You
could have discrete and continuous state
spaces for like a variable and it could
be the same underlying aspect of the
world like temperature in the room. That
could be a continuous variable between 0
and 100 or it could be just the integers
0 to 100 or the thermometer reading
could be
continuous or it could be constrained to
be discreet or even the the agent's
belief about temperature or what actions
it's going to do. It could be um what
angle will my elbow be at? That could be
a continuous value or it could be I'm
going to have my arm at the low, medium
or high discrete position. So it's kind
of like a 2x two matrix. Discrete and
continuous time handling and then the
state space that's under time evolution
could be discrete or continuous. And
there's kind of a natural affinity for
discrete state spaces in discrete time.
That's like kind of the the grid world,
like the computer science fantasy is
just like this discrete chessboard
undergoing rule-based evolution. Like
chess is a exact example of the discrete
discreet pieces exist at discrete
locations at discreet times. And then
there's kind of this natural affinity of
the continuous continuous
where you just have like fields and
flows
and everything is nicely differentiable
in state space and in time. But you also
could have a discrete variable
in continuous time.
So that would look like
here's an example of a continuous time
linear system.
And there's a there's a latent variable
that's going to switch between mode one
and mode two. And basically mode one is
a low variability setting. Mode two is a
high variability setting.
So at all time steps it's like it's in
mode one and it's outputting a data
scatter and then that flips into mode
two and you go into a high variance
mode. That's that's a latent discrete
variable switching in continuous time.
And then of course the other fourth case
would be you have a continuously valued
number
in discrete time. So that would be like
you're using PIMDP
and at every time step the agent is
going to evaluate
how safe is the situation and it's like
and then the next time step it's 655.
So it's it's it's a decimal number but
it's being discreetly updated in time
steps.
So that's the kind of like lay of the
lands of chapter seven and eight which
and the reason why it makes sense to
have those two is time is the special
variable
handling temperature as a continuous
number or a set of ranked integers or
high medium low
those are all kind of like ordered sets.
without the continuous ordered set is
infinite and then the integer one is
finite and then the one with high medium
low is is like very low number of finite
state possibilities but they're all kind
of like there's a lower to a higher
continuum. It's just a question of
whether you have a smooth gradient, like
does the volume knob have a smooth
slider or does it have clicks, but
that's roughly similar.
And the big question for for the
formalism, let alone how it gets
implemented on on computers,
is the difference is in the time
handling. And then figure 4.3
is kind of like the Rosetta Stone
figure
because it lays out the structural
isomorphism
between the chapter 7 discretet time and
chapter 8 continuous time approaches
very blatantly laying them out to show
their architecture all the time. I know
that
>> they had a few rain few too many rain.
>> So they have a structural
affinity, but then that's like kind of
the provocative nature of figure 4.3
is like these two models, they do
different things. It's like here's the
here's this the MP3 file and here's the
vinyl, but it's the same song.
But they're totally different in how
they get played out.
But they they have enough overlap where
you can kind of do the magic eye thing.
If they were side by side, do the magic
eye thing and like see how there are
parts that play identical or analogous
roles.
And so that gets brought up in chapter
4. And then chapter seven and eight is
kind of like the divide and conquer. And
then it gets stitched back together in
chapter nine with the empirical data
part. But seven and eight focus on
these two pieces.
But anyone else just write a question or
go for it. Yes, please. Carrie,
>> um I just need to get this sort of
question out of my mind. Um
when I first learned programming and
setting up models, um uh the amount of
computing power was always a major
constraint in setting up models that
that we were always sort of forcing
regardless of whatever we were observing
into
simpler formations in order to match the
amount of computational power we So, as
time has gone on and we have more
computational power with computing, um,
and this question like I I like your
example of of analog versus digital. Um
and again just to get me through this
chapter and this so so what's being
presented in this book is discrete and
continuous time and the conversation
about what would be sort of the optimal
model for the conditions we're modeling
um and whether it's more appropriate to
use discrete or continuous.
are are those models generated without
the constraint of computing power and
then we then we kind of constrain them
after the fact or do we set up our
models based on the fact that we know
that we're going to be constrained by
our data?
>> Yeah, that's that's an awesome question.
So the the mo one mode is to
write out the model in the way that's
going to be the um best map
representation
and then take ameliating steps to deal
if there is a computational challenge.
For simple models, it's unlikely to come
up even on a personal computer, but
there are certain situations where
computational costs could increase. And
so this is sort of the computational
complexity estimation area, which is
like if every time step takes a certain
amount of compute, then you get a linear
increase in compute with a number of
time steps.
If every
time step deeper that planning is
happening, you get an exponential
increase in the number of policies to
consider. Then you have an exponential
increase
in computational complexity. If you're
running replicates, it's a linear
increase in the number of replicates. So
between changing features like how many
time steps is the simulation going to
run, how many replicates
of of parallel um execution to run. Um
those are some of the or then then
there's kind of modifying things within
the simulation like make the planning
horizon shorter or make the state spaces
smaller.
Then there are even further moves that
you can make like you can do sampling of
policies rather than evaluate them all.
So like
there's so many situations there's no
there's no rule rule but if you're going
to go the kind of chapter six approach
where you're writing out the state
spaces of your variables and everything
like that and then you can do profiling
as you run the first implementations and
it's like okay did that take a hundth of
a second or did it take 10 minutes to
run.
Um,
as the as the state spaces grow larger,
there's going to be some
more resources required in CPU cycles
and in memory.
And then the computational complexity
question is basically
does it grow linearly,
does it grow exponentially up or does it
grow kind of saturating up? And then
again like if you were taking the model
to be published or you wanted to do
parameter sweeps, you could run like the
small, medium, and large model for 10,
100, 1,000 time steps.
And then you get like a heat map of how
long it takes. And so then that makes it
empirical
um
exactly what resources are required.
But suffice to say, for small state
spaces, like for matrices that are just
several to tens large,
if you're
in that kind of a of a zone,
then
models will run
almost instantaneously on today's
hardware.
And the main place where I mean the main
resource intensive
challenge
on the inbound on the perceptual is if
you're getting like a big data input
like the difference between getting a a
a binary signal versus getting a 4K
video feed.
So
when there's um highdimensional input, a
common approach is to use a neural
network to map that highdimensional
input to a lower dimensional state
space. And that's kind of the approach
of the variational autoenccoder
even outside of active inference.
So that helps get to a more manageable
state space on the inbound And then
usually the main challenge for resources
and compute on the action side is when
there's either a lot of actions to
select from
or when there's a lot of time steps of
planning.
And that's because pi the the policy
if we have four options at each time
point like we're in a grid world
then we have four expected free energies
to calculate but then if we wanted to do
a planning horizon of two we'd have 16
to calculate and then if we had three
we'd have 64 to calculate etc. So that's
the exponential increase in the number
of EF calculations.
And this is one of the fun things is
like you can through chapter 6 write out
the state space of all of these
variables. Like we're going to get an
integer coming in. We're going to map
the integer to high, medium, or low. And
then we have turn on the air conditioner
or don't. and we're gonna plan over two
horizons. Like back of the envelope, you
can you can sketch out
exactly which calculations are going to
happen. Like we're going to take that
integer value and we're going to we're
going to have some matrix that has 100
by 3 and then we're going to have that
3x3
and then there's going to be two slices
in the B matrix. So it's like actually
the computational complexity estimates
are straightforward.
It's just and that helps you get very
quickly to where there are possible
bottlenecks like the large observation
spaces or the large action spaces or
planning.
One of the key differences with the
discreet time is like again thinking of
chess as the paradmatic discreet time
setting that is where planning can be
made the most explicit and that's where
you get the exponential blow up. Whereas
in continuous time
there there is not planning
as such.
This is uh the Taylor Swift series
as it is now known. Um the the the way
that the continuous time
uh
looks forward and back is with the
Taylor series
like approach
which is basically successive
approximations
to the derivatives and just expanding
out
the the this thread.
So,
the plus side of the Taylor series based
look ahead or or back is you get all the
lines. You get infinite look ahead for
free or just for for for this for one
one uh cost.
But the downside is you actually aren't
considering counterfactuals
and you need secondary metrics to assess
how likely is your look ahead.
How likely is the look ahead to be
actually
in a confidence interval?
So the continuous models are like that's
that's why they are um
that's why they often are found lower in
the hierarchy
where they reflect continuous valued
inputs like pressure or temperature and
then continuous valued actions like
effort or angle of a joint. Right.
And then for discretized planning
there's a discrete
and that that um type of continuous on
bottom discrete on top
that is um it was live stream 46 and
that was this kind of um
exploration of of folk psychology
and just they mapped that exact.
See if there's a
not of the generative model.
They have that type of model and they
discuss it. Um yeah. So
summary, small state spaces unlikely to
be an issue
just like you can run a tiny language
model on a old computer.
But if you want to have a huge language
model, you need more resources.
But if they're smaller models, you never
have an issue.
just just kind of reviewing it but raise
your hand or just write in chat. So
8.2 two goes into this classic pair of
equations which is the observations
depend on
a latent state
plus a noise term.
So that's like the EEG data or the fMRI
data intensity at a given voxil. The
actual empirical observation depends on
some generating function of a latent
space and measurement noise.
And then how that latent state changes
through time. X dot
is a function of
the state of the latent variable at that
time and sort of a cause operator
plus a noise term. So this is like the
neuroiming observation depends on the
neural state. Change in the neural state
depends on the neural state
and that distinction between what is the
empirical data and its generation
and then what is the latent data giving
rise to empirical observations and how
it changes through time. That's like the
minimal classic setting.
Um
8.2
is very similar and just replaces this
kind of generic causal model uh inter
intervention intervening variable to
explicitly be action.
Okay.
Then there's going to kind of stay with
that theme of the empirical data being
generated by G and the change in the
latent state being generated by an app
and give a special a special case a
simple special case which is a point
attractor.
Um
this is is basically when um x is going
to be the the uh
v is the set point here and x is like
the location of something. So this could
be like a a gravity well or spring.
um
when x is less than d
x goes positive and then when x is more
than v it goes negative.
So it's it's linear on either side
here.
that gets expanded a little bit
with that same V minus X
theme,
but instead of now being basically like
the absolute value around a point
attractor,
now it's a Newtonian mechanical
Hook's law spring
around an attractor. So it's like we
have a slinky that's hanging down and
then if you push it up it'll wobble but
come back to its resting point. If you
pulled it down it would wobble and come
back to its resting point.
So that is how the causal
aspects of the system get encoded into
the dynamics of the latent variable and
then those are used to generate
observations.
8.3
goes into dynamical systems and like
stochastic or probabilistic dynamical
systems, linear or nonlinear dynamical
systems.
There's a ton of
of work in and textbooks and everything.
But here's one reason why the continuous
why this isn't a continuous chapter is
because we're talking about systems
where the discretization is inefficient.
Like if there was um a three-dimensional
linear system
with a thousand options on each, you'd
have a million state space and you know
or just a billion. Um yeah, they say
limited space in the book. We cannot do
justice to the large body of
work, but they show some pieces. So now
this is going to be in two dimensions.
This is the spring
in two dimensions. So V is going to be
the spring attractor and X is going to
be the location of of a two-dimensional
joint.
Um so
V could be the top down the this is from
chapter 5 invoking the spinal cord
reflex.
The descending prediction of the motor
system sets the attractor location V
and then
through um error minimization of
propriceptive inputs coming in
you get ballistic movement towards the
set point
through that spring-l like dynamic.
So this is kind of like that slinky
and then the top down the descending
mental prediction changes where the set
point is and then the slinky adapts to
where that settles in to where that set
point is
because of incoming proprioceptive
signals
and the imperative to reduce the error
difference
between the descending prediction of
where the joint ought to be and the
incoming observation of where the joint
is. So that's like expectation
fulfillment
based motor behavior
through
predict predictive error resolving motor
loop with descending motor predictions.
And then like you could these mu subx
could be coming from a discrete model or
continuous model. So that could be like
I'm gonna I'm gonna want my hand in
place one and then two and then one and
then three and then you'd see the arm
move in those ways. Okay.
8 point box 8.1 is very
fascinating about sensory attenuation
and it kind of goes into a little bit
more of this situation which is like
when
should there be a dominant influence of
the top down prediction and when should
there be more of a top down influence or
bottom up influence of the measurements
coming in. So it's like
all the proprioception is saying I am
sitting in a chair
I am not moving and then the top down
prediction goes I am moving.
So if the bottom up is being attended to
then the top down anticipation is going
to get corrected in the face of evidence
to the contrary. Hence no movement is
executed.
However, this is kind of like when you
engage the clutch in an automatic or in
a in a manual car
or when the eyes happens,
there's a transient attenuation
of the
incoming stimuli
that kind of gives this brief
opening for the top-down prediction to
be enacted
even though it is not being borne out by
the propriception.
But then once but then then the clutch
can get re-engaged once the movement has
already begun.
And this empirically happens in motor
action and in in isades being a special
case of of motor action.
Then the chapter pivots to a classical
ecology setting,
the locka voltera dynamics. So here's uh
a winnerless competition
with plants, herbivores, and carnivores.
So it's like kind of a food web, food
chain situation.
And there's three continuous
functions
that have relationships to each other.
So this could be like three economic
variables or this could be three hormone
levels or three uh population levels of
a of a ecosystem.
And then these two panels are like the
state space in three dimensions is is in
a cube. And then this is like the shadow
or the projection of the cube
looking at just the plant versus the
herbivore where it mostly follows this
limit attractor
or the herbivore versus the carnivore.
So this is just showing
although you're just getting
instantaneous
relationships,
you can get sequential and iterative and
unfolding dynamics
through that. like even if there was
just um the relationships of two
hormones or of three hormones, you still
could get structured unfolding
just from the fixed relationships of how
those hormones work.
Um, and two more behavioral examples of
where the lockable terror model is used
and and the reason why it's brought up
is because it's often used to model the
relationships of brain regions in their
activation. So region A will activate B,
B activates C, and then C represses A.
So if they all start at that baseline, A
would start to pump up B. B would start
to pump up C. But then once C starts to
get rolling, it would shut down A, which
would ultimately feed back to shut down
C. But then once C was off, A would come
back online. And so that's the
winnerless competition part. And uh the
left
example, it's it's sometimes unclear
with the black and white images. So the
papers are cited but there's a eyelink
uh associative learning example
and then there's a writing kind of a
cursive writing example.
Um,
box 82
is is uh again a kind of mathematical
note
and
it it it's a little bit of a standalone
note, but it has to do with how do you
optimize the beliefs
in continuous time and like the the
integral is that's the whole thing with
like the infantessimal and is there a
really infinitely small variable? Are
there continuous functions or are they
just kind of small trapezoids?
Um okay then they pivot from the
mockable terra
co c co c co c co c co c co c co c co c
co c co c co-ependent dynamical systems
with with cyclic attractors or limit
attractors into the chaotic system of
the loren attractor
whole cool story
um
great work and discussion in the um
stochastic chaos and mark all blankets
uh paper from I guess 21.
Yeah.
Yesterday, four years in a day ago.
Um
just to show this approach works
for doing inference even on a chaotic
system where small changes lead to large
outcome differences
system. So this is exactly analogous to
the
here we have a threedimensional
dynamical system and then we have two
two-dimensional projections of it
here. Same thing there's three
dimensional systems time evolution.
Little bit hard to tell which the three
lines are but they are three. and then
two projections of Y on X and Z on Y.
And not Lauren's
has been used in this bird song example
where basically there's two birds that
are that are jointly singing.
And
it's not exactly the level of
open-endedness of uh natural language
conversation of humans
because both of the birds are
aware of a song that basically needs to
be upheld or they expect it to be
upheld. And then it's like turn taking
is reflected by being in one attractor
where one bird is singing and then it
but that represses its own singing
eventually and then that flips over uh
to the other bird singing
which is um in in in
bio
that's that's sometimes called a
repressillator.
But we can see a similar kind of
pattern, but it's a two two-step
refracillator.
Um that idea of the generalized
synchrony
which is like it's not correlation.
Correlation is an example of synchrony
but correlation is lock step where two
things are correlated when they're
exactly moving in the same level. But if
two things were um moving oppositely,
they would have a negative correlation.
Or if there was some other like a u
mapping between two variables, the
overall correlation might be zero
because the best fit regression would go
straight, but the mutual information
between those two variables could be
very high. So generalized synchrony is
like a more generalized version of
correlation that's based on mutual
information.
rather than linear regression slope
8.5 just says yes legos work like this
you can plug in you could have a
continuous continuous model you could
have discrete discreet you can also have
discrete on top and then continuous on
the bottom
So here the palm DP the chapter 7 on the
top level is going to discreetly
determine which target is going to be
set at for basically the spring
attractor.
So here it's uh an is secade look
example where there's a discrete
decision of where to look at discrete
time points
and then there's ballistic movements
to in continuous time
to look at where the the intention is to
look.
Um here's another small mathematical
side note box about a Gaussian mixture
model
and
there the Gaussian is an amazing
distribution. It turns out that any
distribution,
you know, asterisk, etc., can be
approximated by a mixture of Gaussians,
even if it has a bunch of different
humps or a very nonlinear shape.
Um, and so you can kind of compose
Gaussians and overlay them on the same
variable. That's a Gaussian mixture
model. You can also have nested uh
Gaussians and that's called a
hierarchical Gaussian model. So because
the Gaussian or the normal distribution
is so well behaved statistically
and it so well represents
distributions with a central tendency.
It's
used all the time.
And then they review some of the papers
that have applied continuous time models
to
mainly human and mamalian
settings.
So this chapter reads the most like a
um
stochastic
dynamical systems text review.
But it also just shows that's what's so
cool about treating action as a variable
in a statistical model
is like variable two of these. This
could be you know cortisol the sound
level and
your effort in flexing your quadriceps.
Not exactly those three variables, but
you could ask how are those variables
through time related? And then the fact
that two of those variables or you know
the fact that one of the variable is an
external variable, one of them is a
sensemaking variable and one of them is
an action variable. there's a unified
handling of all of them
versus artificially splitting
the signal processing problem from the
control theory problem.
So it's a little bit of a read between
the lines because the examples that come
up are largely like okay we have a
spring attractor
we have a lock of terraen attractor
and a nested model and then an
application of a discrete continuous
model.
But it just speaks to how
unified and and nonsellacious this is to
handle perception, cognition, and action
in continuous and discrete time,
which is where we get at the end of
chapter 8.
So they're a good pair of chapters. It
revisits this kind of chapter 7, you
know, chessboard, grid world, computer
science, rule-based evolution,
state transition concept.
Um, and that gets kind of complemented
with this more continuous
dynamical differentiable perspective.
And then in practice you can
mix and match them.
And one of the directions of the the
field and tool development is to make it
easier to compose those models.
any just
section of eight. Anyone wants to just
or a thought or a question they had on
it?
Should
we by default, Sylvia, start with a
discrete time model?
Um,
as sort of usual, it depends what you
want to ask.
Um, for example, in chapter 7 with the
rat and the T-mase,
like
by modeling this as a series of discrete
time steps, start location and then go
to one of the locations or go to the
queue,
it's not saying, well, but you could
have made a continuous model of the of
the rat moving in space.
So when there are like checkpoints or
milestones,
the discrete can be an enormous
simplifier
or like if there's like zones or phases.
Like we're going to study the the
probability of being
hypoglycemic
or normal blood sugar range and just
like modeling the transition in or out
of there.
that is just going to be like a 2x two
matrix. So that's going to be super
simple and interpretable
versus trying to mix a line
to do that.
So if you're dealing with something
where the differences um between time
points
are discrete
then yes most of the software resources
are going to be discrete time
discrete state spaces or continuous
state spaces.
But then if you um want to have an
example where at every time point along
a continuous line,
you want to have a value that's
changing.
So, like, is it is the situation more
like a chess game or is it more like
you're tracking the location of of a
floating thing in the pool?
And then, okay, so it's more like a
pool.
And then what would be the pros and cons
of overlaying the chessboard on the
pool?
Well, if we just overlay a one by one
chessboard, it's going to be useless. If
we overlay a 1 million by a million,
that's where we get into that
computational challenge
and we lose interpretability and we're
just calculating these large matrices.
But if there's some discrete
approximation
to space andor time,
it's very often done.
and this is kind of a a key buried line
basically that continuous dynamical
systems are a plausible continuous
system that might underwrite the
discrete sequential dynamics.
So that's like
again we have the vinyl record and we
have the digital song.
We could and it just um it's just a you
know a note being a different note being
played.
If we were to overlay them, what we
would like to see would be we have a
line a continuous line and then exactly
on the line are the discrete time
points.
So it's it's kind of like the the the
beads on a necklace
versus the actual string.
And then just which mathematics or which
software are going to make it easier to
work with just the beads locations
versus the strings location.
The discrete time you get the transition
matrix
that describes how states go into the
next
state,
but you don't get derivatives
in the same way.
Okay, any last uh questions?
Okay, awesome. I will